Guide to the Kathryn Greenberg Papers 1991-2021 MS 3215
New-York Historical Society
Kathryn Greenberg papers
1991-2021
New-York Historical Society
Greenberg, Kathryn O.
MS 3215
1 Linear feet in 1 record carton
678 Megabytes (3 files)
The Kathryn Greenberg papers hold publicity materials, annual reports, photographs, news articles, letters, and other documents related to Greenberg's philanthropic and leadership connections with the Cardozo School of Law, New York Legal Assistance Group, Hospital for Special Surgery, Center on Aging at New York Presbyterian, and other institutions.
Arrangement
The files retain the labeling from the original accordion files delivered to N-YHS by Kathryn Greenberg, though the contents have been rehoused into archival folders. The files are arranged roughly by type of institution/philanthropic matter: legal (especially Cardozo Law School), educational (other than Cardozo), and medical/aging.
Biographical / Historical
Kathryn Adele (Olson) Greenberg was born in Minnesota. She attended the University of Minnesota and graduated from the University of Colorado in 1968, majoring in Art History. She went to Los Angeles for graduate school, then moved to New York City to work on Wall Street.
In 1979, Olson entered Benjamin N. Cardozo School of Law at Yeshiva University, graduating cum laude in 1982. She worked for Shea & Gould as a trusts and estates lawyer. In 1987, she married Alan C. ("Ace") Greenberg, the head of the financial firm, Bear Stearns.
In 1988, Kathryn returned to Cardozo Law School as a Supervising Attorney at the Bet Tzedeck Clinic, which provided student lawyers to help low-income people with legal assistance. Seeking to move beyond the resource constraints inherent at Bet Tzedeck, Greenberg left in 1990 to start New York Legal Assistance Group (NYLAG) to provide free legal services for low-income New Yorkers. She remained Chair of the organization until about 2001 when she stepped down.
Greenberg was a member of Cardozo's Board of Directors from 1998-2000 and 2003-2010. She was Chair of the Board from 2004 until she left the position in 2010, becoming Board Chair Emerita. That same year she received Cardozo's Award for Extraordinary Leadership. Along with her husband, Alan (who died in 2014), Greenberg was a philanthropist, donating substantial time and funds to the Cardozo Law School, other educational institutions, medical facilities, and other institutions.
(The above note was based on documents in the collection.)
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Kathryn Greenberg, 2022. The acquisition of the Greenberg papers was an initiative of the Diamonstein-Spielvogel Institute.
Scope and Contents
The Kathryn Greenberg papers hold publicity materials, annual reports, photographs, news articles, letters, and other documents related to Greenberg's philanthropic and leadership connections with the Cardozo School of Law, New York Legal Assistance Group, Hospital for Special Surgery, Center on Aging at New York Presbyterian, and other institutions. The container list provides a complete list of the institutions and initiatives involved with a further sense of the content.
Related Materials
New-York Historical also holds the Alan C. Greenberg scrapbooks and related material, donated by Kathryn Greenberg in 2018 and 2021. Though the scrapbooks center on Alan, Kathryn appears extensively, including in connection with their joint philanthropic endeavors.
Legal services.; Philanthropists.; Annual reports.; Brochures.; Files (digital files); Photographs.; Benjamin N. Cardozo School of Law; Cornell University. Joan and Sanford I. Weill Medical College. Center on Aging; Hospital for Special Surgery. Center for Skeletal Dysplasias; University of Minnesota -- Funds and scholarships.
- Cardozo School of Law (4 folders), 2004-2021 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1-4)
  Scope and Contents
  Holds annual reports, etc. reflecting Greenberg's chairmanship of the Board of the School of Law and other financial support/initiatives, including the establishment of a scholarship fund, the Kathryn O. Greenberg Immigration Justice Clinic, and the Kathryn O. and Alan Greenberg Center for Student Life. There are several publicity materials, press articles, and other documents about the immigrant justice clinic and its social importance. There is one DVD of 'Welcome to Cardozo,' a video of orientation activities for Fall 2007 students; the DVD is restricted, but the transcoded MP4 digital file is available for viewing.
- "Welcome to Cardozo" MP4 digital file, 2007 (Digitalfolder MS3215)
  Digital files preserved from the DVD in the above Cardozo files.
- Medal. Cardozo School of Law, Board of Directors Chairman., 2004 March 3 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
- Photograph album. Opening of Kathryn O. and Alan C. Greenberg Center for Student Life (Cardozo School of Law), 2007 March 7 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
- Yeshiva University. Honorary doctorate, 2005 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  Convocation program, congratulatory letters, photograph album, and related documents re: Greenberg's honorary doctorate from Yeshiva, 2005. The file also holds a CD of the convocation that is restricted, but the transcoded MP4 digital file is available for viewing.
- Yeshiva Convocation MP4 digital file, 2005 (Digitalfolder MS3215)
  Digital files preserved from the CD in the above Yeshiva University/Honorary Doctorate folder.
- Roy Lantigua, 2007-2012 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  Articles, court decisions and other documents concerning Roy Lantigua, a New York Times "Neediest Case" for whom Greenberg was appointed co-property guardian. Also some documents for Cardozo Law's Guardianship Clinic, which developed from Greenberg's exposure to Lantigua's case.
- New York Legal Assistance Group (NYLAG) (2 folders), 2000-2022 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9-10)
  Annual reports, articles, publicity pieces, and other documents about NYLAG. Includes a 3 page reflection by Greenberg on the beginnings of the organization she founded.
- Brown University, 1997, 2004 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  Two letters re: the endowed Kathryn Greenberg Fund and related Lecture.
- University of Minnesota, 2012-2021 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
  Documents concerning the establishment by Greenberg of the Herbert E. Olson Memorial Fund to provide scholarships to students from Bemidji (Minn.) High School attending the University of Minnesota Twin Cities. Also includes fund financial data, publicity material, some thank you letters, etc.
- Carnegie Library Renovation, Bemidji Minnesota, circa 2019 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
  Pictorial booklet related to the renovation, funded by Greenberg, and history of the library.
- Hospital of Special Surgery (HSS) (3 folders), 1994, 2005-2021 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14-15)
  Publicity, reports, proposals and other documents related to the Kathryn O. and Alan C. Greenberg Center for Skeletal Dysplasias at the Hospital for Special Surgery. A DVD about the Center is in the folder and is restricted, but the transcoded MP4 digital file is available for viewing. A 7:26 videocassette about the Center is in the file and is restricted because of the fragility of the media.
- Hospital of Special Surgery MP4 digital file (Digitalfolder MS3215)
  Digital files preserved from the DVD in the above HSS folder.
- Council of Senior Centers, 1991-1992 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
  Documents about the Greenbergs receiving the Good Citizen Award.
- New York-Presbyterian Center on Aging, 2017 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18-19)
  Photos of the new Center on Aging, the pre-construction space, and the former Wright Center. Also publicity material about the new Center, which was funded by the Greenbergs.